{"tossups": [{"question": "In inertial confinement fusion, a theoretical hole in a hohlraum would accurately model this phenomenon. Bose-Einstein statistics were first developed in order to resolve a problem explaining this phenomenon. The constant 2.9 times 10 to the negative -3 meters Kelvin is used to find the peak wavelength of this phenomenon in Wien's displacement law. The spectral distribution of this phenomenon as a function of temperature is given by (*) Planck's law. The power of this phenomenon is proportional to surface area times temperature to the 4th power, according to the Stefan-Boltzmann law. For 10 points, name this form of radiation emitted by objects that absorb all incident electromagnetic waves.", "answer": "blackbody radiation [accept blackbody after \"radiation\" is read; prompt on radiation by asking \"from what kind of source?\"]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In one story by this man, Margot's schoolmates lock her in a closet, leading her to not experience the title phenomenon that happens once every 7 years. In addition to \"All Summer in a Day,\" this author wrote a work in which the psychologist David suggests that the HappyLife Home be shut down. Another story by this author includes silhouettes of daily life such as depictions of two people doing yard work and two children playing a game of ball. That story is based around a (*) computer-run house that still functions after a nuclear fallout. This author wrote another short story in which George and Lydia are eaten by lions after their children lock them in the \"nursery.\" For 10 points, name this American author of \"There will come Soft Rains\" and \"The Veldt.\"", "answer": "Ray Bradbury", "subcategory": "Short Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This leader's unseating was compared to \"firing the Prime Minister for a traffic ticket\" after being accused of election fraud by Raj Narain. During one campaign, this leader adapted an opponent's \"remove her\" slogan to a slogan translating to \"Remove Poverty,\" Garibi Hatao. The Shah commission investigated forced sterilizations this leader conducted during a 21-month period known as the (*) Emergency. The Smiling Buddha nuclear tests were conducted by this leader. This leader ordered the invasion of the Golden Temple during Operation Blue Star, which led to her assassination by her own Sikh bodyguards. For 10 points, name this first female Prime Minister of India.", "answer": "Indira Gandhi [prompt on Gandhi]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This religion believes that a savior figure will be born from a maiden who enters Lake Kansava. This religion believes that substances contaminated with nasu should touch neither the earth nor fire. In this religion, both the living and the dead will be required to walk through a river that feels like warm milk for righteous people during Frashokereti, when the Saoshyant will also come. This religion believes that two four-eyed dogs guard the (*) Chinvat bridge. This religion places dead bodies on dakhma, or towers of silence, where they are eaten by birds. The central text of this religion is the Avesta, which tells the story of the eternal conflict between Ahura Mazda and Angra Mainyu. For 10 points, name this dualistic Persian religion.", "answer": "Zoroastrianism [or Zarathustrism or Mazdayasna or Magianism; accept Mazdaism before \"Mazda\"]", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "Two components of the change in this quantity formed a pattern called the \"Russian Cross\" when measured in many former Warsaw Pact countries. Hans Rosling created the documentary Don't Panic in order to explain his views about why changes in this quantity are not that concerning. This quantity is multiplied by affluence and technology to give the impact on the environment. This quantity slightly declines in the fifth stage of the (*) demographic transition model. The exponential increase in this quantity can lead to famines in a Malthusian trap. It's not age, but this quantity's \"pyramid\" is somewhat inverted for Japan. Demographers study this quantity. For 10 points, name this quantity that is roughly equal to 7.7 billion people.", "answer": "human population [or number of people; accept clear equivalents]", "subcategory": "Social Science", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "This artist created a landscape work featuring three figures wearing red, blue, and green, symbolizing love, faith, and hope respectively. Gottlieb Christian Kuhn designed five baby angels and the eye of God for the frame of one artwork by this artist depicting a Cross in the Mountains. In addition to Chalk Cliffs on R\u00fcgen and the Tetschen Altar, this artist painted himself as an old man with a fur coat in an allegorical painting depicting (*) five boats of varying distances. This artist of The Stages of Life portrayed the shipwreck of the HMS Griper in The Sea of Ice and painted a man with a walking stick standing on a precipice before a cloud-covered landscape. For 10 points, name this German Romantic painter of Wanderer Above the Sea of Fog.", "answer": "Caspar David Friedrich", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A novel by this author contains a metaphor comparing the author's country to a speeding sled called a troika. The protagonist of that novel by this author is believed to be either Napoleon or Captain Kopeikin. The title character of a story by this author is caught with a forged passport while riding to Riga. That story by this author opens with the barber (*) Ivan finding the title object in his bread. One novel by this author sees Chichikov bargain for the titular Dead Souls, while another sees the title body part travel around St. Petersburg after detaching from Major Kovalyov's face. For 10 points, name this Russian author of \"The Nose.\"", "answer": "Nikolai Gogol", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A group led by Cadex Herrera created a work that depicts this man seated in front of a sunflower on a blue background. Stanley Watts designed a seven hundred pound bronze statue depicting this man sitting on a bench. Chris Carnabuci designed a statue depicting this man inscribed with a caption describing how (*) \"knees should be used to pray.\" Those statues were vandalized by a group promoting \"LIFE, LIBERTY AND VICTORY,\" the Patriot Front. A statue dedicated to this man depicting a bronze fist was recently added to a square named after him in Minneapolis. For 10 points, name this man who was memorialized in murals after he was killed by Derek Chauvin.", "answer": "George Perry Floyd, Jr.", "subcategory": "Current Events", "category": "Current Events"}, {"question": "In the leadup to one battle, this country performed a series of parachute operations known as Operation Castor. After failing to carry out orders issued by Christian de Castries, a soldier from this country named Charles Piroth committed suicide by hand grenade. Outposts of this country named Beatrice and Gabrielle were the target of a battle compared to a \"rice bowl\" by one side's leader. Vo (*) Nguyen Giap defeated this country's forces at the Battle of Dien Bien Phu. One of this country's colonies was split along the 17th parallel after this country's Fourth republic lost the First Indochina War. For 10 points, name this colonial power that fought against its former territories of Laos and Vietnam.", "answer": "France", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A poem by this author personifies \"Great Time\" who \"sits enamored at your feet\" and begins \"amidst the rush and roar of life.\" The speaker of another poem by this author asks \"oh to what foreign land do you sail\" and requests that person to \"take away my golden paddy.\" The thirty-fifth poem of a collection by this author describes a place \"where words come out from the depth of truth\" which ends by describing a (*) \"heaven of freedom\" and commands \"my Father, let my country awake.\" That collection by this author had a prologue written by W.B. Yeats and opens with the line \"thou hast made me endless, such is thy pleasure.\" For 10 points, name this Bengali poet of Gitanjali.", "answer": "Rabindranath Tagore", "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "In one story, Kiyohime turns into one of these creatures and kills a Buddhist monk after he rejects her. The legendary sword Kusanagi-no-Tsurugi, one of the three imperial Regalia, was pulled from the tail of one of these creatures. The kami of the sea, Ryujin, is depicted as one of these creatures, leading to these creatures being associated with (*) rain prayers. Susano'o legendarily killed one of these creatures by using 8 vats of sake; that one of these creatures had 8 heads and 8 tails and was called Orochi. For 10 points, name these serpent-like mythological creatures that do not have wings nor breathe fire like their Western counterparts.", "answer": "dragon [accept serpent or snake before mention]", "subcategory": "Mythology", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "During a satellite conflict of this war, French troops massacred residents of a British frontier town in the Raid on Deerfield. A treaty allowing for the exchange of \"English cloth\" and \"Portuguese wine\" was negotiated by John Methuen during this war. The British were granted a monopoly on slave trade to one country following this war, the asiento. A palace in Oxfordshire is named after a battle in this war where the Duke of (*) Marlborough prevented the capture of Vienna, the Battle of Blenheim. The American theater of this conflict is known as Queen Anne's war. The Treaty of Utrecht ended this war. For 10 points, name this war where Louis XIV contested Philip V's ascension to the throne of an Iberian nation.", "answer": "War of the Spanish Succession [prompt on Queen Anne's war before mentioned]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This quantity of a system equals the sum of the chemical potential times surface excess of each component in the Gibbs isotherm equation. This quantity for a pure liquid has an approximately linear relationship with temperature, according to the E\u00f6tv\u00f6s rule. This quantity equals the increase in Gibbs free energy per increase in surface area at constant pressure and temperature. This quantity is traditionally measured in (*) dynes per centimeter. Adding a surfactant decreases this quantity. High values of this quantity allow some insects to walk across lakes. For 10 points, name this quantity that describes the cohesive forces between molecules on a liquid's surface.", "answer": "surface tension", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This opera's overture begins with the cellos playing an eighth note A up to a long F followed by an eighth note E and a long D-sharp. A chord pioneered by this opera consists of F, B, D#, and G#. In this opera, Kurwenal reminds one character about the death of Morold. This opera ends with the aria \"Mild und Leise,\" which is also known as the (*) Liebestod; the singer of that aria in this opera is promised in marriage to King Marke of Cornwall. In this opera's first act, the servant Brangane gives the title couple what she believes to be poison, but actually turns out to be a love potion. For 10 points, name this Wagner opera about the two title lovers.", "answer": "Tristan und Isolde [accept Tristan and Isolde]", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The SOCAR towers in this country's capital is composed of two towers of different heights that curve around each other as they rise; that capital of this country is the largest city below sea level. This country's national language uses an upside-down letter e to represent the sound /\u00e6/ [\"a\" in that]. This country contains the autonomous exclave of Nakhchivan. The Flame Towers are in this country's capital, which lies on the (*) Absheron peninsula. This country's tallest mountain, Mount Bazard\u00fcz\u00fc [baz-ar-doo-joo], is located on the border between it and Dagestan. The disputed region of Nagorno-Karabakh is surrounded by the territory of this country. For 10 points, name this country to the east of Georgia and Armenia whose capital, Baku, is on the Caspian Sea.", "answer": "Republic of Azerbaijan", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "One vein that drains this organ is compressed between the aorta and mesenteric artery in Nutcracker syndrome. This organ's function can be assessed by measuring serum creatinine levels. In response to hypoxic conditions, this organ stimulates the production of red blood cells by releasing erythropoietin. Countercurrent multiplication maintains a strong osmotic gradient in this organ. The pituitary gland releases (*) vasopressin to signal the reabsorption of water into this organ. In this organ, renal corpuscles consist of a glomerulus attached to a Bowman's capsule, which are part of this organ's functional unit, the nephron. For 10 points, name this organ that filters blood and creates urine", "answer": "kidney", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "One composer who played this instrument in Paul Whiteman's orchestra composed a suite with a final \"Cloudburst\" movement that was used as the score to the Disney film Grand Canyon. A \"Charleston rhythm\" is featured in the first movement of a Concerto in F for this instrument. Ferde Grofe played this instrument. A performer of this instrument wrote an opera in which Remus saves the title character from being thrown into a (*) wasp's nest. A piece for this instrument was named after a club in Sedalia, Missouri. A jazz band accompanies this instrument in a piece that begins with a clarinet glissando, George Gershwin's Rhapsody in Blue.  For 10 points, The Entertainer and Maple Leaf Rag were written by Scott Joplin for what keyboard instrument?", "answer": "pianoforte [the powermark clue refers to Treemonisha, by Scott Joplin]", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A politician with this surname claimed that \"Ulster is becoming Britain's Vietnam.\" Another politician with this surname and his wife Carolyn Bessette died in a small plane he was flying near Martha's Vineyard. A politician with this surname, who gained the nickname the Lion of the Senate, was accused of killing the speechwriter Mary Jo Kopechne in the (*) Chappaquiddick incident. Another politician with this surname gave a speech on the flatbed of a truck following Martin Luther King, Jr.'s assassination during a presidential primary campaign against Hubert Humphrey. Sirhan Sirhan assassinated that politician with this surname. For 10 points, give this surname of a Massachusetts political family whose members included Ted, Robert, and the U.S. president John.", "answer": "Kennedy [accept Edward Kennedy or Ted Kennedy or Robert Kennedy or Bobby Kennedy or John F. Kennedy Jr.]", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "After being confronted by one character during a parade, this character rebuffs \"He is a dreamer. Let us leave him. Pass.\" In a speech about this character, another person exclaims \"O Judgement! Thou art fled to brutish beasts\" before saying that his \"heart is in the coffin\" with this character. In one speech, a statesman recounts how this character was presented with \"a kingly crown, Which he did thrice refuse\"; that speech, which is intended to (*) bury [this character], not to praise him,\" begins, \"Friends, Romans, countrymen, lend me your ears.\" This character ignores the warnings of Calpurnia and a soothsayer who says to \"Beware the Ides of March.\" For 10 points, name this title character of a Shakespeare play who exclaims \"Et tu, Brute\" before being stabbed.", "answer": "Julius Caesar", "subcategory": "Drama", "category": "Literature"}], "bonuses": [{"leadin": "One type of these objects' death line is displayed on P-P-dot diagrams. Changes in rotational frequency cause glitches in these objects. These objects are found in a system that emanates gravitational waves, the Hulse-Taylor binary. The maximum mass of nonrotating types of these objects is approximately 2.2 solar masses, according to the (*) TOV limit. One type of these objects rotate more than 700 times per second in their millisecond variety. The lighthouse model explains how one type of these stars, pulsars, emit radiation from their poles. These stars are more dense than white dwarfs and are the result of a core-collapse supernova. For 10 points, name these stars that are composed of uncharged particles. ANSWER: neutron stars [accept millisecond pulsars before \"pulsar\"; accept neutron after \"star\" is read] <Melkumian, Other Science> <ed. Wu>  Answer some questions about the Argentine composer Alberto Ginastera. For 10 points each:", "parts": ["One of Ginastera's most famous works is based on a narrative poem by Estanislao del Campo, in which a gaucho attends a performance of this opera. In this opera, one character repeats the lines \"Ah, I laugh to see myself / so beautiful in this mirror\" in the aria \"Ah, je ris de me voir.\"", "Ginastera drew upon gaucho culture to write a work in this genre called Estancia, much like Aaron Copland drew from cowboy culture to write works in this form like Rodeo! and Appalachian Spring.", "Ginastera heavily used a \"chord\" named for this instrument in his Opus 47, a concerto dedicated to Carlos Barbosa Lima, a virtuoso of this instrument. This instrument was also played by Andres Segovia."], "answers": ["neutron stars [accept millisecond pulsars before \"pulsar\"; accept neutron after \"star\" is read]", "Faust [it's by Charles Gounod - the aria might be better known as the \"Jewel Song\"]", "ballet", "classical guitar"], "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science"}]}